The most interesting big new trend is in
personal agents.
>> We're in this world where we're so
excited by what Chachi did with turning
things into conversation and now these
agents we can get in our messaging apps
to turn them into more conversation.
There's this incredible paradigm.
>> About half of Americans report using AI.
Around 4% of US consumers are paying a
subscription to an AI product. The top
1% user is spending $93 per month
personally on their personal credit
cards on AI. The reality is people are
now building software. They're building
these really rich products. They might
be using their agents to write some of
that code, but when they're delivering
this whole experience to a user, it is
much more than just a shim on the model.
The
>> run rate that OpenAI has reached through
advertising. What does that tell us?
That would previously take a company
years and years and years to get to even
after launching an ads product. What I'm
fascinated to see in terms of the
evolution of the ads product is
Welcome to the A16Z podcast. I'm Elena
Burgerer and I'm joined by Olivia Moore
who's the author of our ongoing top 100
consumer AI apps report and Josh Elman
on our consumer team. Today we're
digging into the seventh edition of this
report. Who's paying for AI? Why the big
assistants are heading in different
directions? and whether personal agents
can turn everyday errands into the next
big consumer business. Team, thanks so
much for joining. Um,
>> thanks so much for having us.
>> Olivia, let's just get right into it. I
would love to hear uh your top takeaways
from this report.
>> Yeah, so this is the seventh time we've
done this list. The very first time we
only ranked all global websites that
were AI native by just traffic, like
hits on the website. Uh, and that worked
then because the way that almost
everyone was using AI was like a prompt
box product in a browser. We've had to
evolve that a lot over the last few
years as AI expands. So, this list is
our most expansive yet. Um, we added
revenue data for the first time. So, we
worked with the EBIT data to get
specifically consumer card spend data.
So, not accounting for enterprises or
SMBs. Uh, and we ranked products by what
consumers are actually paying for. I
think for me the biggest takeaways from
this report is on a traffic basis, it
looks like a lot of these products are
kind of settling. Um, we only had 11 new
products across the web and mobile list
combined, which is the least we've had
in every uh in any of the prior editions
of the series. But the spend data really
introduced a lot of new variables
because of those 50 that ranked for
spend, 29 of them were not on either
traffic list. M
>> um and that also I think kind of works
towards or connects into the other big
conclusion of the report which is just
how much of a power user game consumer
AI is right now.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. That's something that's funny. We
we also recently released our state of
markets and something that Sarah Wang
actually commented directly on um is she
she said hey there there's such a power
law game happening now. It's happening
at the enterprise level and it's
happening at the consumer level. Um, so,
uh, one thing that's probably notable
is, yeah, we have the fewest number of
newcomers on this list and it seems like
the space is oifying, but I think the
past few months things have actually
been picking up a little bit more and I
think I think the most interesting big
new trend is in personal agents. Um, so
what are you seeing? What are the big
shifts that are happening?
>> Yeah, it's funny. The last report that
we did um it ended right before the cut
off of when openclaw traffic would come
in. So we had done kind of like a retro
before we published the report and we
had found that it would have been very
high up in the rankings. Um, and this
time actually openclaw is nowhere in the
rankings because the traffic has
>> completely declined as I'm I think that
the team was acquired by OpenAI. they're
probably working on, you know, the agent
assistant products there, but also it's
kind of been overtaken, I think, by some
of the both other attempts at proumer
agents like Grockbot, um, Town has some
fantastic agents. Dots now by OpenAI,
which is new. Um, but also on the
consumer side, we're finally seeing
things that I would feel comfortable
giving to a family member and telling
them that they can safely use. Most of
those also because to your point this
consumer assistant trend has literally
been the last 3 weeks to a month. A lot
of those didn't appear uh on the ranks
yet. But we did pull the data to see
what's happening with them. And it's
been um very very fast growth and yet
still not quite reaching the mainstream
user is what I would say. You know, I
think we're in this really interesting
era that did really change at the end of
last year, beginning of this year with
OpenClaw, that AI went from something
that we were using as a tool to enhance
our productivity to maybe search for us
faster, something that would actually
get things done for us. And I think
OpenClaw was an incredible pioneer to do
this and I know they're still doing a
lot of work through their open source
foundation to continue to advance that.
But it really turned a lot of heads on,
wait, what can these products actually
be? And we were seeing people buying Mac
minis. We were seeing people run all
their own data with their own local open
cloud. There was a huge run on that. But
it was really inspiring to kind of feel
this new energy of what is possible. And
you know like most trends you know that
spark happens. It takes a little while
for those first products to get built.
It takes a little while for the momentum
to then start getting those even
released in the market for users to see
them. And so, you know, in some ways
though, this report is showing like
that's what we're talking a lot about,
you know, on our podcast in Silicon
Valley. But this really does a great job
representing what's happening in the
broader world and and that, you know, I
do think the truth is AI really is
showing up everywhere. Even if there's
not a lot of new entrance, all the
entrance are all getting so much bigger.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think probably the biggest
things on when we talk about pure
consumer assistance uh the biggest
developments have been muse and instinct
I would say although there's many other
fantastic products that we kind of list
in the report that have also you know
poke was a very early pioneer here.
Exactly. Tommo is has a very big
audience and is doing incredibly well.
Um Instinct had announced like 100,000
users growing 10% day over day. uh they
had announced like 40% of users
connected a credit card in the first
three weeks and they were spending you
know over $1,000 on average in their
first month. Um Muse is interesting
because uh in many ways very successful
launch especially within the tech
community. I think the number was like
500,000 downloads and 250,000 active
users in the first 12 days or so. But if
you look at it versus Threads, which was
another, you know, somewhat recent big
splashy meta launch, um it just it still
pales in comparison in terms of appeal
to the average person who doesn't work
in tech.
>> Yeah. So, if you look at the the
downloads, um Muse is still only US and
Canada. So, we grabbed the threads US
and Canada downloads only. In the first
22 days or so threads, it had about 16
million downloads and Muse is still
sitting around 5 million. over that same
time period.
>> Is the distribution mechanism different?
Like I remember with threads, it was
already tied to your Instagram account
and there was kind of this like very
natural distribution. Is are they trying
a similar strategy with Muse or is it
just a different distribution strategy
too? I mean, from I'd be curious what
Josh thinks, but from my point of view,
it's not as aggressive for sure. Uh, and
also part of that is because there's a
much higher cost to serve these users.
So they don't want it to get too big too
fast. Well, and I also think threads
very much had a critical mass effect,
which is if they didn't get a lot of
people on it communicating quickly, you
don't actually get to that leverage of a
new network starting to form. Whereas
Muse is still such a personal tool that
you know, they're pushing it and there
it's very exciting to kind of even see
this early just adoption and people
having these experiences. And again, if
you were using OpenClaw in January, you
were having incredible experience using
Crockbot when that first launched
earlier this summer, spring, you were
having these incredible experiences. And
now we're seeing as you know I think
Olivia said you know our moms our
families you know people who don't just
live on the tech what's next in AI cycle
and I think that's what's really
exciting about this consumer. I I assume
when we do this again next time we're
going to see massive adoption. But I
think it hasn't needed to push as hard
to have that early network effect. But
then I also think about what's going to
make these things stick around for a
long time. And it is going to be things
like network effects and marketplaces
and all the businesses you can interact
with those agents. That's going to be
really transformative too.
>> Yeah, this is one of the things we talk
about a lot when it comes to consumer
agents and assistants which is I think
they are getting kind of the compounding
effects of building out a platform or at
least it seems like they are in terms of
the ecosystem of other apps that are
available and more easily usable by the
agent. We've seen that cut both ways.
Like Amazon is like, "We're not going to
allow Muse
>> to kind of browse and purchase products
on our site, but also, you know, Muse
has already hundreds of other
partnerships with different,
>> you know, to be able to buy things on
Shopify."
>> Exactly. Yes. Um I don't I still don't
feel like any of the assistant products
have unlocked persontoperson network
effects. And part of this for me is like
this software knows us more intimately
than any other product in the past
>> based on email, but also like I find
myself telling extremely personal things
to my AI. And so there's kind of this
natural um tension between the more
useful the product is to you as the
consumer, the more it knows about you
and like then do you really want to
introduce that into other contexts with
other people. It's the same thing as
like many people have a separate chatbt
work account and personal account and no
one has quite cracked that yet.
>> No. And I think you know as we talk
about consumers and AI, privacy, safety,
security are becoming more and more
important. I mean there's obviously the
overall trends of you know trust in AI
and and this kind of belief that AI is
good for the world that is in some ways
you know affecting adoption and
affecting some of the excitement around
these products. But on a very personal
level, if you don't trust the thing that
you're giving it your most intimate
access to, your email or your life or
your credit card and it might do rogue
things that you wouldn't expect or share
things with other people you wouldn't
expect, you know, that's going to be the
biggest impingement on these things
really growing is as massive consumer
apps. So, it's a we're in a fascinating
time where we're all learning these new
norms and these are norms that like as
people we're actually very good at it.
We're very good at knowing what
information we're comfortable sharing,
what information if somebody gives it to
us, what information that we're trusted
to be able to pass on to somebody or
should be protecting and keeping
ourselves. And we're just like all of a
sudden expecting software to do this,
too. It's a it's a very, you know,
interesting new set of things we're
learning.
>> Yeah. Well, you you both just brought up
like two interesting sort of facets of
this. One is like there's this
endogenous force which is all of the
platforms and how they allow agents to
interact with them and then there's more
like this exogenous force of like how
how comfortable am I using this and and
how maybe I mixed up indogenous and
exogenous one is on the outside one is
on the inside
what the platforms are doing and one is
how you feel about it or how you feel
about the agent and I I'm curious which
which do you think um is going to get
resolved sooner and and who's like whose
onus is that? Like whose whose
responsibility is resolving those kinds
of questions? I think what the platforms
are capable of is improving faster than
true consumer willingness to use them.
Um, which we've seen kind of throughout
AI so far. It's interesting because a
lot of people are like seeing these
numbers that founders of these assistant
products are posting that it costs like
hundreds or thousands of dollars a month
to serve a user and like how is that
possible? Um, and I was stumped as well.
But I uh have been working with David
Pollon who runs assistant benchmark
who's fantastic. So
>> there's a recent podcast with him.
>> So basically what he's done is he's
created a website where they track I
think over 170 agents. I checked it last
night. It's probably like 200 something
this morning. Um, and they he has users
kind of use them and then rank them on
success on different tasks. But the
other really interesting thing that he
does is he hosts kind of group chats and
communities of early adopters of these
agents. So he has a group of I think
it's 1500 plus users. And he pulled some
cool data for us which is like what are
they doing with agents? what are they
talking about doing with agents? And the
vast majority still the number one use
case was coding and technical automation
even for these consumer assistant
products like like Muse and Instinct.
And so under that framing it's like oh
of course it costs that much. This is
like when we talk to some agent or
assistant products that are uh aimed
towards the more mainstream consumer,
they're seeing costs in the tens of
dollars, not the thousands of dollars a
month. So um I think that is maybe a
representation of the fact that we have
a very long way to go in terms of
consumers getting comfortable with these
products
>> and I think you know I think people
who've been coding and have been working
with AI I mean it's been such an
incredible enhancer and that shows up in
a lot of the data you know on the on the
top 100 here like it's incredible and
then we've people who've been able to do
that have had these great ideas for all
the other things in their life but when
you just hand this to somebody new it
feels like a blank box and it feels like
what should I do with this and maybe
there's examples of getting a
reservation or booking a flight, but if
you're not actively seeking a
reservation or booking a flight, it's
hard to figure out how to personalize
it. And so much of what we do as people
is we learn from others and we get these
great ideas and we try the other things
people tell us. So much of how social
media has worked is people put things on
social media and other people see that
and they try the same thing and then it
kind of spawns these effects. I try they
make a little riff on it and then those
riffs become you know cascading
snowballs and that's how great ideas
flourish and with AI because so much of
it's so personal we haven't even seen
any of that flourish and yet you know
outside of areas like coding and
productivity you know all of the
creative work you know I I created this
incredible video and how'd you do that I
use AI um you know there's so many tools
that do that that that are you know been
growing and are here but it's so
interesting that you know now we have to
figure out how to mainstream this for
not the you know millions and millions
of people who are using these and paying
and and everything but for the you know
tens hundreds and you know hundreds and
hundreds of millions
>> if you look at broad usage data now
about half of Americans report using AI
and about 25% of Americans think they
are interacting with AI probably on
close to a daily basis uh but the
spending data is much more concentrated
so it depends on the source um our Yepit
panel shows probably sub 5% around 4
1/2% of US consumers are paying a
subscription to an AI product. Some of
their sources say as low as 2 or 2 and a
half or maybe a little bit higher. It is
expanding. So that's like doubled from a
year ago. Um but that spend is still
extremely concentrated. So even within
that top 4.5% of people who do spend the
top 10% of those are like more than half
of the revenue and the top 1% are 20% of
the revenue whereas the bottom 50% are
like 16%. Right? So like the top 10% of
users are driving this market. This was
the other interesting thing about
revenue data is we were able to look at
it kind of like on a almost person
byperson basis what it looks like. Who
are these people who are spending on AI?
>> The top 1% user is spending $93 per
month personally on their personal
credit cards on AI.
>> Wow.
>> And the median is spending $25.
>> And again, all of this is within the
only the 4.5% that are spending at all.
Yet also was helpful for us because we
could see what products are they
actually spending on like on a on on a
personal basis. And probably
unsurprisingly, it was mostly developer
tools, um, productivity tools, creative
tools, things used to like build, make,
sell.
>> Um, things like NADN, Granola,
Higsfield, Manis, those all were way
over represented amongst the top
spenders. I
>> mean, in a way, this is actually really
cool. I mean, even though these numbers
aren't everybody yet, like we're
enabling this whole new generation of
makers of people who are, you know, not
just using this for work, but actually
using their personal credit cards to
code things they they never coded before
to make art, make videos, make content,
and, you know, really have this power of
making. And so, it's actually in some
ways, you know, while it's all still so
early, it's actually really cool how
much making is going on that people are
actually so excited they're willing to
spend. If you're spending $900 a month
on a set of AI tools, you're really
using that to like hopefully make things
faster, better, have more ideas in your
head coming to life than ever before. So
that's kind of like when I when I was
looking at the categories between
creativity and coding like
>> you know that's actually hopefully
really really powerful.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Well, I I I think this is a point
that's really important, which is I
think developers and coders are people
who are naturally attuned to sort of ask
how do I get leverage over this thing?
How do I build a product that allows me
to get leverage over my time? And AI
obviously supercharges that. But it's it
is a specific kind of mindset, I think,
and it's a specific kind of world view.
And I think the part of part of my
understanding of these numbers is it's
still a world view that gets reflected
only among a small smaller group of
people. And the question might be just
like how do you expand that world view?
How do you help people understand like
here are all the ways you can get
leverage over your time and over your
life?
>> We talked about this a little bit in
this report in terms of areas where we
have not yet seen AI native startups pop
up or categories where we haven't. Um,
>> Eugenia, who's one of our portfolio
CEOs, runs a company called Wabby, which
is fantastic. She has this great quote.
I'm probably going to botch it, but it's
something like people, most people
aren't looking to save time. They're
looking for ways to spend their time.
>> Um, like this is why social media,
entertainment, Netflix, Tik Tok, all of
these, YouTube are so are the most used
consumer products that we have. And I
think that much of what we've seen in AI
thus far to your point is like how do I
do this thing a little bit faster, a
little bit easier, a little bit more
impressively. And that's not an
incredibly compelling daily or hourly
active value proposition for most
people.
>> No, I think I think this, you know,
saving time is still very, you know,
hyperproductivity people who are focused
on, you know, work or being creative.
But I'm also seeing this next wave of
people who are maybe used to be coders.
They're no longer maybe people who, you
know, want to make videos but never
quite mastered the, you know, ProTools
and Adobe Premiere or something else or
they're all of a sudden able to sign up
for these things and take the ideas in
their head and make them happen. So, I
do think, you know, we're starting to
see these rise up. And again, as you
know, I look at all these numbers as
we're still so early. Yes. and and the
fact that we're even here and that we're
talking about how, you know, big some of
these companies are and that 1% of
people are spending $900 a month. Like
>> I see these as harbingers of what's to
come as more people feel empowered, as
more people feel like they can create
where it doesn't it's not about saving
time. It's about spending the joy of
like actually willing this thing into
reality. You know, we there there were
all these jokes of, you know, oh, when
people were in this like the peak phase
of everybody was using their open claw
for the first time, their agents, they'd
walk around with their computers and
their laptops. They had to keep them
open and they they were like, I'm not
sleeping. I'm coding and I'm making
things, you know, more than I ever have.
And I think that's starting to, you
know, again, shows up at the top of the
data, but I do think it's starting to
show up sort of everywhere this list. I
actually don't necessarily want to see
that 4.5% of people paying for AI
products directly expand,
>> which is maybe controversial because I'm
like invest in consumer AI products and
I'm a consumer AI maximalist.
>> But the reason I say that is because
>> substantially all of the consumer AI
revenue thus far has come from direct
subscriptions.
>> Um, like on this list, we looked and it
was like, you know, 85% or something of
our web list monetized via
subscriptions. Another 62% monetized via
kind of credits or token extra usage
payments. Only like 13% had ads or other
options where like you are the product
instead of paying for the product. And
that's like a if you look back at the
history of the consumer internet, that's
like a pretty unnatural inversion. Like
almost all of the really big consumer
technology companies that we have now
make the vast majority of their revenue
from ads or from transaction fees, not
from subscriptions. Because I think the
truth of it is most similar to the fact
that not everyone is looking for a
coding tool to help them, you know,
start a business or or create and sell a
product. Most people don't have the
funds or don't want to spend their funds
on software. If you look at the top 20
consumer uh subscription products
globally, Chachi BT is already on there
which is crazy in like three and a half
years of growth. Almost all the other
ones are media companies
>> or big platforms like Amazon or even
Uber things like that uh where you have
a very frequent purchase behavior. So I
actually am a big believer that we need
to move. We have transcended the need
for everyone to buy a subscription to AI
and we need to see these other business
models come back.
>> You know, I think we're still at the
early days of inference costs coming
down. We're still at the early days of
people finding ways to run lowerc cost
models to build great products. And as
they do that, you know, a lot of the
other business models that have always
been on the internet from, you know,
transaction fees and ads will finally
start working. But we we need that to
happen. And that's I think where we're
still, you know, there's so much
learning and and so so much that like,
well, if it's going to cost me a lot to
serve, at least let me just charge money
so that people pay for it became sort of
an early default.
>> Yes.
>> I mean, you can probably speak to this
from seeing many prior eras of the
consumer internet, but like it used to
be, at least for me as a consumer
investor, if a company was making money
in the first 5 years, it was like, whoa,
what's happening? The the rule was like
let's build density of users and because
they cost near zero to serve, we can
then wait and make money via ads or
start charging for transactions once we
have liquidity and density. And that
just isn't the case given how high COGS
are.
>> No, I think I think this cost thing is a
is a really interesting challenge and
companies get afraid of growing too
fast. Yeah. like they actually if they
grow too fast and they don't have meters
on how they're charging for it, you can
actually have out of control spend that
can be very very hard to manage. So, you
know, it's created this this very
different shape of what we see in the
top apps and the top 100, you know,
traffic and everything right now. But
again, this is again we're all still so
early. There's so much to build and
learn and bring cost down and bring
value up and introduce advertising and
introduce other ways to to spend money.
And by the way, if if it is we subscribe
to these services we love and that's
actually what we get continual value
from, that's amazing, too.
>> I think this is a a great transition to
talk about ads. Yeah,
>> your uh consumer uh top 100 report had a
really really interesting fact in there
which was the run rate that OpenAI has
reached through advertising. They're at
a billion dollars now in in annual run
rate on on advertising and
>> what does that tell us? You know,
>> again, the number was from August and so
there's probably a chance that it's
reasonably higher even a month or so
later. But they have been very slowly, I
would say, rolling out ads um with kind
of a network of partners and they're
already at, you know, a billion billion
in annualized run rate. Like that would
previously take a company years and
years and years to get to even after
launching an ads product. I think
there's two interesting things there.
One, they have real density now. So I
think the last reported number a few
days ago was 1.2 billion weekly active
users, which is like a real density. And
then the second thing and what I'm
fascinated to see in terms of the
evolution of the ads product is
hypothetically they should be able to
charge more and have higher conversion
rates because they just know so much
more about you as a user and chatbt has
launched things like login with chatbt.
I think a wallet is coming, things like
that. And so you could imagine that um
it becomes a much more compelling value
prop for the advertisers and then that
just like juices the ad business even
more. Uh but we'll see. It's very early
days there.
>> It's early days and I think you know
there have been some really funny
conversations about ads and AI. if you
are talking to this incredibly personal
thing and then it's like let me tell you
about health and let me introduce you to
this like crazy product that can help
you you know lose weight fast like
that's not building trust with AI and so
I think the other really interesting
thing is like how do we as a ecosystem
these products are so different they're
so much more personal than ever before
they're giving you answers that are
customtailored to what you're doing and
what you're asking about and what it
knows about you that actually
introducing ads has been done very
definitely I've actually been really
impressed with the open AI roll out of
ads what I've ever seen an ad? It's it's
very clearly labeled and it actually
feels like part a natural ad to the
conversation that I'm having. And I
think we're also, you know, one of the
other shifts is people are starting to
rely on, you know, chat with a lot more
for a lot more queries. It might have
used to been like look up a fact or tell
me the history of this thing or help me
with my homework, not necessarily
problem solving and things we're
advertising, but now people are going it
to it for real advice or shopping or
trying to figure out exactly, you know,
where they want to go or what they want
to do. And those are great opportunities
when you're in a discovery mode where
ads are actually often a great answer to
help you solve that. And so a lot more
of these commercial queries and these
commercial intent creates that too. But
again, it has to be done very very
deafly, not this weird interruptive very
personal experience I'm having that ads
just get shoved into the conversation.
>> Um, I'd be I'd be super curious to how
the unit economics on ads work. like
presumably it's a it's a lower cost
question or lower cost compared to you
know a coding or or something like that
or image gen. Um, so, so for OpenAI, you
know, what what kinds of margins are
they seeing on ads is a super
interesting question.
>> Um, I curious also, Josh, what what kind
of ads do you see? Because I I I don't
get any ads. I guess I I I guess I pro
enterprise so we don't Yeah.
You know, I I was doing a bunch of
travel research recently and um was was
going to be in New York for a few days
and I just started seeing some ads for a
couple things that were going on in New
York that I might have wanted to do and
I just found that really useful and like
I've started using it more for
commercial shopping. I was looking for a
a special um keychain that would have a
really easy separation for a valet key
and I was having trouble finding this
actually on Google and I finally was
like, "Let me just go ask ChachiBT." And
I went back and forth and I was
describing what I wanted and started
giving me some really good examples. And
at the end I was like, great. And I'd
also love one that's made in America.
And it actually found this incredible
like option from a factory in Detroit
that often makes a lot of other metal
work and other stuff that had this like
really cool key for me. And like it was
one of those things that if I had never
had that chance to really go back and
forth and actually have that
conversation and if there had been other
ads that got no no ads were presented in
that conversation, but it was entirely
open for ads that they would have helped
me find stuff and eventually I went to
this website. I'd never heard of that
company before. Um and it was a great
experience.
>> So interesting. I feel like we may see
as they lean into it, OpenAI uh being
able to do crazy good targeting uh on
consu like even better than I think Meta
which previously was like best in class
for this just because they knew so much
about you but like you're having this
live conversation with them.
>> I do think that it'll help chatbt but
also I think it will also support a lot
of these more focused almost
verticalized to use the enterprise term
consumer AI products. So another company
that has seen early success in ads is
open evidence which is um an AI product
for doctors and it already has 50 I
think the most recent numbers were 50 to
60% density of US all of all US
physicians on the product and so when
you have that kind of density of a
really valuable audience and it's like a
targeted audience because you know
they're physicians you can I think
advertise really effectively and there
will be and should be more of those I
think.
>> Yeah. Is it is it worth talking and
taking a step back and talking about uh
OpenAI,
Anthropic and Gemini and and sort of
these have these are companies, these
are labs that have been on the list
pretty much since the beginning. Um are
we seeing any kind of evolution in in
the way people are paying for these
products? Um what can we surmise about
the different kinds of users of all
three? Uh super super curious what
you're what you're seeing. Yeah,
absolutely. Um, from the very first time
we did this report, the main conclusion
was like chatbt is the dominant global
user by both usage and revenue on the
consumer side. That continues to be
true. Everything below chatbt has seen,
I think, more movements and more
shakeups. So, chatbt is now ahead of
Claude um around 6x on the web, around
2x uh ahead of Gemini on the web.
probably going forward given a lot of
the usage is concentrated in these power
users who are paying um the revenue
numbers could be even more useful here.
Um, and probably that's one of the
biggest surprises to me in this report
was we got a panel of US spenders and
Claude has actually passed Gemini in
terms of number of paid subscribers
which is kind of crazy given Gemini has
a much bigger install base and user base
overall and it also has like the natural
distribution mechanism of something like
a Google. I think that's a big, you
know, accomplishment of course for
Anthropic. I think it's come on the wave
of a bunch of very successful products
that they've launched over the last few
months like claw design. Uh it's also
come from a lot more press that they've
had starting with the department of war
stuff all the way back in I think it was
February. Um the other main difference I
would say in how these products are
monetizing and again chatbt still far in
the lead by monetization. They have
around three times more paid consumer
subscribers in the US than both Gemini
and Claude. Um, but Anthropic has said
very famously, no ads. So, they're much
more aggressive about subscription. They
have around seven and a half% of
subscribers on the $100 plus per month,
like the max plan.
>> And that's like 1% for both Chachi and
Gemini. And so those users naturally
look different and are doing different
things on the product even in that paid
user base.
>> Should we talk about creative tools? And
um I think one thing that's interesting
is actually all of the big labs have
gotten really good at creative tools.
And one thing that that actually like
Anthropic kind of famously abstained
from but then somehow achieved anyway
was like creating an image model or
video model but now people are making
images and videos because coding is so
good at creating like images and videos.
Um so it's interesting that you know
they didn't build the diffusion model
yet they're still capable of doing uh
image gen but but about the the pure
creative tools the the companies that
have kind of like verticalized in that
category what are we what are we seeing?
>> Creative tools is very interestingly
distributed in terms of who is
succeeding where. So there's a few
categories of creator tools or maybe
modalities is the better term where the
labs have not focused energy and
attention for many reasons we could
discuss. Uh a lot of those are around
audio. So like text to speech music 11
labs inso are now very reliably near the
top of our traffic list and are also
ranked very highly in our spend list.
The labs have so many things to do.
They're building coding agents. They're
building AGI. Does it make sense at this
point for them to deal with all of the
IP headaches that Suno has had to go
through and launch a competing music
model? I don't know. And in the
meantime, Sunno has been able to kind of
run away with a really strong lead.
>> Yeah. And you know, I'm a big believer
that, you know, the labs are going to do
what they're going to do and they're
going to keep growing and they obviously
are great baselines for everything. But
in so many of these markets, you're
seeing really specialized products that
are really focused knowing who their
audience is and what they're doing
that's able to build really custom
things. You know, if you want to make
music just for fun or for something that
you're really producing, Sunno is an
incredible tool and it speaks to you
from the moment you start using it
through the end. You know, 11 Labs, if
you need voice and audio within the
product that you're making, it just has
a way of working and and interacting
with it that feels completely different.
when you look at a bunch of the video
tools, um, you know, when you look at
design tools, even like Figma, like
they're so designed to to use deeply for
the thing you're trying to express
yourself and it speaks to designers, not
to people who, you know, want to just
skip that step. And I think we're going
to see so much more value from these
really bespoke interfaces where the
software layer of all the things you can
do and the things you save and the way
you interact with it become really where
the value sits, not just the models.
>> Yes. So this is the second category I
think of creative tools which is um
images and video that looks different
from audio. On images I think to your
point like OpenAI has really leaned into
images quite successfully like images
2.0 is very very good both for image
creation and editing and then of course
Google with the various iterations of
Nano Banana and VO. I think they have
candidly taken away a lot of the
highlevel consumer traffic that was
previously going to these standalone
image generators. Um so like Midjourney
was fairly high on our first ever
rankings. It has fallen off the traffic
rankings completely but to your point
empower users if you look at the revenue
rankings midjourney is back. So people
the power users still want the model
that they feel has taste has an
aesthetic sense and that they're able to
tune in a really specific way. Um, and
then that brings us to video, which to
me is kind of like a wild frontier right
now because
uh, Chinese companies that can train on
any data and do uh, have a real
advantage. Video is just so complex to
generate with like the visual, the
sound, the visual and the sound synced
and looking a specific way. Uh, that I
think like the more data you have to
train the better. They've been
successful there thus far. Um, I think
more broadly in creative tools, I'd be
curious if either of you have
experienced this, but I have recently
been asking Astra and other really
powerful models to generate or create
uh, generate or edit creative for me and
it does a very very good job and it will
go tool call to elsewhere on the
internet. And so I think that creative
tools that are agentfriendly
uh, and agent accessible are going to
increasingly see really compelling
tailwinds.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's actually crazy what you
can do if you just like empower an agent
and just say like, "Yeah, install
whatever you want to install." Um, I had
it I actually had uh Astra and 5.5 go
like headtohead and animating some stuff
for me and like
>> it it was just like it knew exactly what
to do. It's like yeah. So,
>> and and what I love about this is, you
know, this is the tinkerers, the people
at the edge are figuring out these
capabilities and we're going to build
products over the next year that are
going to show up on these lists because
they're going to take all of this
complexity of what you can do and
package it up in a way that makes it
really easy to use. And like that's
this, you think of this gap of like all
AI versus consumer AI, it's exactly this
this movement of packaging these up and
building great product experiences.
Yeah. that really turns it into into
these things that sustain.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And I guess it it has to
start with the tinkerers and then they
post on X and then you know six months
later we get a real like product and
startup out of it or like you know 12
different startups all competing.
Outside of the web window there have
been a big proliferation of of mature
products. So there's Granola, uh there's
Whisper Flow, there's Superhum.
Um what what are you kind of seeing
there? And then obviously the ones that
exist in chat and messaging, so in
instinct. Um what are you seeing when it
comes to distribution and what are you
seeing just when it comes to the kinds
of products and users that they're
approaching?
>> Yeah, I think there's two maybe
interesting threads to pull on here.
when I I wrote this piece called maybe
six nine months ago called the great
expansion which is basically like why
are consumer companies becoming
enterprise companies so quickly uh like
things like uh crea you know replet um
11 labs gamma these products previously
like Canva took six plus years to have
real team and enterprise revenue and
what's happening is that they're very
successful and growing via PLG
whisperflow and granola another great
examples there and And because they are
kind of work productivity related, they
get pulled into enterprises and then the
founders are like, "Oh, we got to add
privacy and security and a team plan."
But it's very effective, very lowcost
distribution. And again, it works really
well for these tools that are can be
used personally but are like work
adjacent. Um, I think things like
Whisper Flow and Granola and Superhum
are another good example of this trend
we've seen in general, which is
incumbents being unwilling or unable to
cannibalize their existing interfaces.
The classic example of this is Google.
Like we haven't really seen them
reinvent Docs or Gmail or calendar for
the AI age. I think it's even happening
with open AAI and anthropic where they
have been much less successful in
anything that is not a launch within
their existing chatbt or codeex or
claude or claude code interfaces.
>> Um so and I know many of them have you
know attempted to incubate killers for
these many startups but I think it is um
difficult from a product perspective for
them to innovate beyond that especially
when they have so many other things on
their plates. I think all that's true
and I think you we now as we get used to
some interfaces we're just still in such
a period of incredible reinvention like
a lot of the reason we've seen so much
growth over the past year year and a
half is the models got so much better
and the models got so much better so the
people who had been spending time
creating these incredible interfaces
that were easy to use that were that
were natural that were you know easy to
share and get a bunch of your team on
and you know whisper flow and granola
were just so easy to get started with
you then would say oh my gosh now
they've gotten so much better as the
models have gotten better that the
products utility gets so much better
too. And so we're kind of this this
incredible you build something great,
but it may not do everything you want
because the model capabilities weren't
quite there. Then the models get better
and your product gets to explode in
demand and utility and this kind of
rising tide lifts everything. And so to
think that you know we only have one or
two companies that can build that
experience layer I think is what this
sort of report sort of debunks. Now
those are certainly some of the top
companies and these very general use
cases but it's you know the reason that
so many other things are growing is
there's so many interfaces that get to
be reinvented and and the sort of rising
tide list everything and then you know
the infra value may still go to the
model providers or may go to the other
things that are serving inference and
there's a whole different conversation
there but what consumers are adopting
are things that work for them and are
easy to to use and bring into their
lives.
>> Yeah. Maybe to also make the to continue
to make the case for startups here. Open
AAI and Anthropic in many ways are
startups, but they have been so
successful that they have become big
companies with thousands of people and
there are just so many extra
consideration like a a a larger ship is
harder to kind of steer or to turn
around. Yeah.
>> Um and so I think that's like one of the
companies on our revenue list this time
is Plaude which is an AI notetaker
device. um that started kind of in China
in the east and now has come to the US
and you buy the device and you can also
buy a subscription. Um OpenAI can and
will do a hardware device but as we've
seen with them it just everything takes
longer when you're a big company. Uh you
have to integrate with maybe other
existing products. There's more checks
and balances it has to go through. So I
do think that the big labs will continue
to be very very successful and there's a
lot more for them to do and I think that
startups will continue to be able to
find these quite big windows of
opportunity.
>> Yeah. And well it also sounds like the
the question for startups is how do you
build a product that as you said Josh
gets better as models get better but
doesn't get cannibalized as models get
better. um which is you know what like
like an interesting kind of sweet spot
to exist in. I mean, part of the reason
that I was so excited to join Andre and
Horowitz a couple months ago was this
belief that the value really now is
moving back to the software layer that
now that we have these incredible models
at our, you know, capabilities and we
can access them, you can build really
rich products that leverage the models
to do it, you know, and there's new
innovations like, you know, Jeb from
Typesafe that allows even developers to
build things in even new ways. is and we
haven't even seen all the incredible new
ideas that can be done when you have
access to a model like that that's fast
that's easy to integrate that you know
gives you code you know are very
structured answers back um and so
because of that now the creativity is
back to the experience the network you
can build the ways that you can serve a
lot of people and bring them together
using the models to be something
powerful but the context and the
community really becomes the asset
there's so much in invention and I I
think almost every category has a chance
to be reinvented and you know some big
companies are going to be able to make
the leap and become the relevant company
for their sector in the AI era but not
all of them will and that's where
startups come in to kind of beat them to
that punch and really be the best new
possible experience.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think to that point I
think a lot about compounding personal
value and hopefully eventually
compounding multiplayer value that
becomes like a lockin to some of these
startup products. One example I would
give is town which is more on the
proumer end of the agent assistant. It
can connect into all your systems,
slack, email, Google drive, understand
kind of the context of you and your org
and then do things for you. Like I use
it to write a lot of my emails, helped
with a lot of this report. And I know
it's easy for people to dismiss things
like this as like, oh, it's just a
harness, which is now the slightly less
derogatory term for rapper, I guess.
>> But Town has built these playbooks of
who I am, what I sound like, that no
other product has, and that I cannot
easily take and migrate over to
something that comes along tomorrow.
Because the difference between an email
that is 99.9%
sounds like me and even an email that's
85% sounds like me is the difference
between spending like 10 seconds to fix
it and like 10 plus minutes. Uh and so I
think that we'll see more products like
Town that do a really good job of
collecting context and acting on that
context to build playbooks around you
continue to be successful.
>> No, I think that's totally right. And I
try to avoid using words like harness
and rapper because because I think the
reality is people are now building
software and they're building these
really rich products and they're you
know they might be using their agents to
write some of that code but they're
actually when they're delivering this
whole experience to a user. It is much
more than just a a shim on the model or
a harness that brings some context to
the model. It's actually a really rich
product and an experience that happens
to now use a model as part of what makes
them able to deliver that. And I think
that's really the excitement of where
that's going to, you know, what we're
going to see on this list. You know,
many of these already are doing that.
And we think really the next wave, they
are all going to be these companies that
have built so much more value. And the
model is something that is, you know,
just one piece.
>> Yeah.
>> Um Olivia, I think you referenced this
this chart that you made, but maybe we
can bring it up. is all of the white
space that still exists for, you know,
just all the product categories that
exist in web 2 and the pre-ai age and
maybe you can just talk through some of
these categories and um where are the
big opportunities?
>> Yeah, the vast majority of pure
consumers are basically using AI still
as a replacement for search products,
things like Google. Um maybe especially
as you get into education use cases,
kids are using it to write essays. A
little bit more of an expansive use
case, homework help. Exactly. Yes. Or
people in the workplace to write emails.
But if you look at this this chart,
which will show almost all of the kind
of areas where we've seen startups
succeed thus far have been in and around
that theme of getting things done. Uh so
like productivity, photo and video
design and editing, search and answers.
Um, so many categories are wide open.
Uh, and many of those categories are I
would say I would call them network
categories where you need a multiplayer
product. Um, you know, dating is one. We
haven't seen we there are certainly
startups there that I hope and believe
will make future additions of the list,
but there's no one on the list doing
dating now. Recruiting is another one.
And I think of dating and recruiting as
somewhat similar networks actually in
terms of trying to make matches.
>> Um, social AI, we really haven't seen
anything take off. Most of
>> most of social AI is people posting AI
generated content on existing social
platforms. Um, and then I think there's
all of these other categories that are
look maybe more like marketplaces did
like shopping, uh, home buying,
um, you know, retail. We'll have to see
if those end up living in agents like
Instinct or Muse or living as standalone
products or the next ones which there
will be many uh or living as standalone
products or perhaps a mix of both.
Perhaps your agent is calling the AI
native marketplace.
>> Um so I'm very excited about those
things. is I think also categories like
gaming and entertainment, the models
just have not been good enough to
produce content that the average person
likes to watch, which maybe the
exception of AI micro dramas, which are
blowing up.
>> Um, but I think that is coming soon,
too.
>> No, I think that's exactly right. And I
just think we're in this world where,
you know, we're kind of like so excited
by what Chach did with turning things
into conversation and now these agents
we can get in our messaging apps to turn
them into more conversation. It's
incredible paradigm, but when you're
shopping, you want to visually see
options and explore and have things
customized for you and be able to say,
"I really like that, but I wish it had
some piping on the collar or something
and actually have AI helped you both
realize that and maybe even get it made
for you." And like shopping and have so
much invention there. entertainment. I
think we've barely started scratching
the surface of the ability to tell
better stories, of the way to empower
people to be better storytellers that
then creates these incredible networks
of people consuming stories. You know,
Tik Tok was this incredible place where
people came together and just create
little videos. You see people around the
world that you're now watching, but
there's still so much capture in
people's heads that if only they could
express their ideas even better. I is
going to help that and we're going to
have incredible new network. So I feel
like we are just at the cusp of all
these categories and we've needed the
models to get better so that you could
start to dabble in some of these ideas
and invent them. But as that happens
over the coming years and with the new
model capabilities, I still think the
value is going to end up in this
software layer in the process.
>> Yeah, to me this gets back to what we
were talking about of products that help
people save time versus spend time.
Almost everything we've seen in consumer
AI is save time
>> and that spend time those end up often
actually being amongst the biggest
companies if not the biggest ones
>> and so we need that to to exist and many
many builders I'm sure are tinkering
away on that right now.
>> Absolutely.
>> Absolutely. I think that's a great note
to end on. Thank you both so much for
joining and uh absolutely make sure to
check out the top 100 consumer AI apps
seventh edition.
>> Thank you. Thanks for having us. We will
see you for edition 8.
>> Yes. Yes.